<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief testimony for religion shewing that all penal laws, force, and violence against any matters of meer religion and conscience are inconsistant with the doctrines and precepts of Jesus Christ : presented to the consideration of all, but more especially those that may be chosen members of Parliament, that they may see cause to concur with the Kings gracious declaration for liberty of conscience / by a lover of the King and his country, and hater of no man because of his opinion, William Shewen.</title>
            <author>Shewen, William, 1631?-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59950</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3419</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10942</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13788549</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13788549</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101817</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59950)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101817)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 849:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief testimony for religion shewing that all penal laws, force, and violence against any matters of meer religion and conscience are inconsistant with the doctrines and precepts of Jesus Christ : presented to the consideration of all, but more especially those that may be chosen members of Parliament, that they may see cause to concur with the Kings gracious declaration for liberty of conscience / by a lover of the King and his country, and hater of no man because of his opinion, William Shewen.</title>
                  <author>Shewen, William, 1631?-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101817:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEF TESTIMONY FOR RELIGION: SHEWING That all <hi>PENAL LAWS, Force</hi> and <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> againſt any for Matters of meer <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> are Inconſiſtent with the <hi>DOCTRINES</hi> and <hi>PRECEPTS</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt. PRESENTED To the Conſideration of all, but more Eſpecially thoſe that may be choſen Members of Parliament, that they may ſee cauſe to concur with the Kings Gracious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration for Liberty of Conſcience. By a Lover of the King and his Country, and a Hater of no Man becauſe of his Opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WILLIAM SHEWEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101817:2"/>
            <head>A Brief Teſtimony for Religion, ſhewing that all Penal Laws, Force and Violence againſt any for Matters of meer Religion and Conſcience, are inconſiſtent with the Doctrines and Precepts of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Principle of Religion, is Inward, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Divine, not contained in Books, nor taught by the Precepts of Men, being before Books, and the Precepts of Men were inwented, and is in it ſelf Sacred, Pure and Undefiled; Grounded, Planted and Placed in the Heart of Mankind, <hi>by the Sacred, Pure, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled God,</hi> who hath given unto all <hi>Life, Breath and Being:</hi> And in all Nations upon the Face of the Earth, all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therein, who <hi>fear God,</hi> and <hi>worketh Righteouſneſs</hi> are accepted by him; being in the Exerciſe of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, doing <hi>Juſtly,</hi> loving <hi>Mercy,</hi> and walking <hi>uprightly</hi> with God.</p>
            <p>Now tho' God hath ſown this Seed, laid this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Equity, Juſtice, Righteouſneſs, Mercy and Fear towards him, in the Hearts of all Men; yet they are greatly Degenerated therefrom; thoſe plants of his own Right-hand planting, are greatly overgrown with that which is quite contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> with the Weeds and Plants of <hi>Iniquity, Injuſtice, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs, Cruelty, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Diſobedience, Rebellion againſt God, and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101817:3"/>ſo that almoſt the whole World of Mankind is now become Enemies to <hi>God, Nature</hi> and their <hi>own ſelves,</hi> in all Nations, Countries, and Kingdoms, according to the degree of their Degeneration from the <hi>Law, Light, Love, Dread and Fear of the Almighty God,</hi> which he at firſt Placed, Planted, and Engraved in the Heart of Mankind.</p>
            <p>Some in moſt Nations (from the effect of what ſtill remains) have been made ſenſible of their Loſs, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs and Degeneration from the <hi>likeneſs</hi> and <hi>Image of God,</hi> viz. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs, Holineſs, Equity, Juſtice, and Mercy,</hi> &amp;c. And they have been greatly concerned in their Thoughts, Wills, and faln underſtandings, how to gain the ſame again, and have therein invented and ſet up, among Jews, Turks, and Indians, as in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, various ſorts and manners of VVorſhips, and Ceremonies of Religion (ſo called) thinking thereby to pleaſe God, profit themſelves and others, by teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and compelling (if they have Power) the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance thereof, tho in ſo doing they can go no further than <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Cain.</hi> did, <hi>hide and make a Covering with fig-leaves, offer a Sacrifice with one hand, and Murther with the other,</hi> and are no more accepted therein than they were; and the infallible reaſon and cauſe of it is, becauſe, all the Righteouſneſs, and VVickedneſs, proceeding from Mankind in this Degenerate State, are both evil in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>Mankind through his Fall and Degeneration, is ſo Polluted, ſo Defiled, ſo Corrupted, with the ſtinking Leproſie of Sin, that whatever he puts his hand to in things relating to Religion, and the ſervice of God, is abomintion in his ſight; yea, <hi>the very Prayers of the Wicked are ſin:</hi> and out of this Eſtate he cannot help himſelf, he cannot Purge nor Purifie himſelf, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101817:3"/>nor deliver himſelf, by all his working, willing, and running, the Serpent is too Strong, too powerful, too Subtile, and cunning for all Mankind in this Eſtate, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Saviour, without a Redeemer, without a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorer, and Deliverer all Periſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore God in his infinite Love and Kindneſs, did promiſe, and hath performed, hath given, and laid help upon one that is mighty to <hi>Save,</hi> to <hi>Redeem,</hi> to <hi>Purge, Purifie,</hi> and <hi>Reſtore</hi> loſt Man, Defiled, Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Captivated Man into the Image of God again, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Righteouſneſs, Purity, and Holineſs again, and the firſt name this Redeemer and Saviour hath in the Holy Scriptures, is, <hi>the Seed of the Woman,</hi> and his firſt work is, <hi>to bruiſe the head of the Serpent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this promis'd ſeed, <hi>this precious gift of God,</hi> hath many other names throughout the Holy Scriptures; and hath many other works to do, <hi>in</hi> and <hi>for</hi> Mankind, the Serpents head muſt not only be bruis'd by him, but he and all his works deſtroyed and caſt out of the heart of Mankind. And this was and is the bleſſed end of his coming and appearing, even to deſtroy the Devil and all his Works, finiſh ſin and bring in everlaſting Righteouſneſs in the room thereof: Even into the heart and mind of Mankind, which is Gods Throne tho the Serpent the Devil hath uſurped it, my deſire is, that all may come to enjoy that bleſſed Eſtate through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the Saviour.</p>
            <p>VVhich Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour is the Author and Founder of the Chriſtian Religion in the Purity and Power of it; which Religion excels all other Religions upon the Face of the Earth, who are Impure, Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and VVeak, made up of Mens Inventions, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and Traditions, Carnal Ordinances, VVorldly Rudiments, and Beggarly Elements; which had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101817:4"/>and muſt have an end, together with all Hatred and Perſecution about them, for it hath been, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> about theſe things, that thoſe who lived in and under them, have made Laws to force, and compel obſervance and Conformity thereto, for nothing of that fort or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ever did, or can proceed from the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in the Purity and Power of it: Its Fundamental Principles, Precepts, Doctrines and Examples are quite the contrary. <hi>Love your Enemies, Bleſs them that Curſe you, Do good to them that hate you, Pray for them that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitefully uſe you and perſecute your: As you would that Men ſhould do unto you, Do ſo likewiſe unto them. Be like your Heavenly Father, who maketh his Sun to ſhine on the Evil, and on the good, and ſendeth Rain on the Juſt, and on the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt: Love one another, as I have loved you, love ye alſo one another: By this ſhall all Men know, that you are my Diſciples, if you have love to one another. Do good to all,</hi> &amp;c. This is the Tenure of the Goſpel of Chriſt: <hi>Peace on Earth, and good will to Men.</hi> And they only were and are Diſciples indeed, who did and do obſerve thoſe divine Precepts and Commands of Chriſt. <hi>And all that profeſs love to him, and a knowledge of him, and keepeth not his Commandments, are Lyars, and the Truth is not in them,</hi> let them profeſs what they will.</p>
            <p>There is no ground nor foundation for Sangunary Laws, nor for any ſort of Perſecution, Violence or Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty about Religion, in the lovely, meek, quiet, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Spirit of Chriſtianity, nor in the Precepts, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and Diſcipline of it, they have certainly aroſe in Chriſtendom from another Spirit, that hath aſſum'd the Name, and Uſurp't the Throne of God, the Heart and mind of Man, which hath come to paſs, through the working of the Miſtery of Iniquity, Serpent, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, under the Name of God Almighty and Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101817:4"/>the Nature thereof being wanting in all that have been concerned therein.</p>
            <p>For according to the Teſtimony and Phraſe of Holy Scripture, and the experience of Thouſands in this Age, Men have been, are, and may be ſo intoxicated in their Minds, and underſtandings, ſo miſtaken, and Captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedunder that Monſter falt Opinion; ſo corrupted by Tradition, and Superſtitious Education, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that they have been, and are ſaid to be made bewitched given up to believe ſtrong Deluſions, made drunk with the VVine of Fornication, which by the VVhore (the falſe Church) is held forth in a golden Cup to all Nations, according to that not able Viſion of the Divine Apoſtle St. <hi>John,</hi> in his Revelation: read the 17th. Chapter, in a Meaſure of the ſame Divine Spirit of Revelation, or elſe you will miſtake, as all Sectarians hath done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing People may be Spiritually Drunk, mad, bewitched, deceived, miſtaken, blind, and intoxicated ſo far, as to take Truth for Error, and Error for Truth, good for Evil, and Evil for good, Light for Darkneſs, and Darkneſs for Light, true Religion for falſe, and falſe for true, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And proceed in their Converſation and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings accordingly, towards their Neighbours and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, when they have power and opportunity in their Hand.</p>
            <p>Its therefore wiſdom to know theſe diſtemper'd Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and what means and medicine is to be uſed towards ſuch people, and how far the Chriſtian Magiſtrate and Law-maker, are concerned about ſuch things.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> There are two Infallible Signs that people are in the State above: firſt when they are prone to or put for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in a Blind Zeal, to hate, or hurt their Neighbours, or Country-men, becauſe they are not of the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in matters of Religion; nor do not Worſhip after
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101817:5"/>the ſame manner, or in the ſame form and faſhion as they do.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. When they make it matter of conſcience and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to deal with ſuch as are not of their Church and way, as with Weeds and Vermine, and think they do God good Service therein. Theſe are two infallible Signs, that People are Religiouſly mad and miſtaken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> when a Perſecutor (tho by the Authority of the wiſeſt men, greateſt Schollars, higheſt proſeſſors of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, chief Prieſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) was one of the Religious mad men, and they were no better that imployed him, and gave him Commiſſion for the ſame: Notwithſtanding they thought and believed otherwiſe; ſaying, God was their Father, and that they were <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Children, tho at that very time they were doing the Works of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and perſecuting the Seed, and true Children of God and <hi>Abraham;</hi> yet knew not themſelves, what they did, nor what they were, while they were breathing out threatnings, ſlaughter, and Death puniſhing in every Synagogue (or Pariſh) and compelling to Blaſpheme; being as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of himſelf (before King <hi>Agrippa</hi>) <hi>exceeding mad againſt the poor Chriſtians,</hi> perſecuting them even unto ſtrange Cities: all this in his mad Zeal and Ignorance, he with thoſe of his (Religion or rather) opinion, thought was very well done.</p>
            <p>So as hath been ſaid, its wiſdom to know theſe diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd people, which if any lack, let them ask it of God, for it is his own Gift, that makes known perſons and things as they are, in the <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables to give them Names according thereto and to judge righteouſly, and not by appearance, and without this gift of God, no man can know himſelf, nor judge his Brother aright.</p>
            <p>If Education, Tradition, Academical Learning, or a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101817:5"/>profeſſion and imitation of that Religion, which God himſelf commanded, could teach a Man the knowledge of God, or himſelf, thoſe Jews, Doctors and Rabbies would have had it: none in thoſe Ages exceeding them in thoſe things; yet all they attained to thereby, was juſt as if we ſhould ſee a Man believe and declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be the Son of ſome great Prince, or that ſome mighty Monarch was his Father, who had given him Power and Authority as his Vice-gerent, to correct, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, amend and govern, in his Kingdom, when he is no other than the Son of a Vile Butchery Executioner, and is aſſiſting his Father in his filthy Drugery; for Chriſt told them <hi>they were of their Father the Devil, and his Works they did,</hi> even at that very inſtance, when they believed and declared themſelves to be the Children of God and <hi>Abraham, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now thoſe that are, and would be doing the ſame ſort of work; let their pretence be what it will, they are in the ſame condition; tho they may not be ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereof, nor ſee themſelves to be ſuch; for why is a Man ſaid to be mad Spiritually, is it not becauſe the God of this World (that lies in wickedneſs) hath blinded the Eye of his mind, darkned and vayled his Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Judgment, that he cannot ſee, underſtand, nor judge aright of the things of God, and yet believes and perſwades himſelf he can, and by his will and power would force, and compel others to believe the ſame, and to receive his underſtanding and judgment therein, under pains and penalties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is the Nature and Property of a blind mad Zealot.</p>
            <p>Moſt in Chriſtendom are ready to ſenſure <hi>Paul</hi> and the Jews, for their rage and madneſs, cruelty and violence againſt Chriſt and his harmleſs Diſciples, and alſo the Gentiles for their Brutiſh Inhumanity againſt the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101817:6"/>Chriſtians, in the Ten Perſecutions, though they have been and are doing the ſame work, even againſt thoſe that proſeſs the ſame Name together with them, and yet juſtifie themſelves therein, and think they do God good Service thereby, which is an evident Token they are of the ſame ſort, for Perſecutors were always blind.</p>
            <p>And Perſecutions under the Name of Chriſt and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and under pretence of the Propagating and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Chriſtian Religion, are far worſe, and under a greater degree of madneſs, blindneſs, and ignorance, then either Jews or Heathen: they are not only blind and mad, but Drunk alſo, Infatuated, Stupified, Intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and leſs excuſeable then all other Perſecutors up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Face of the Earth, becauſe they do profeſs and account themſelves to be Diſciples of that Imaculate Lamb Chriſt Jeſus, who was always loving, meek, gentle, tender, and kind to all mankind, going up and down, doing good, never harming any, laying down his life for his Enemies, and praying for them, and gave forth thoſe divine Heavenly Precepts and Commandments before mentioned, for all his Diſciples and Followers to obſerve, keep and obey. Now wherever people are found mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing profeſſion of Chriſt Jeſus and his Religion, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe things which are not only Repugnant to it, but inconſiſtent with it: certainly ſuch are in a farther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of blindneſs and madneſs, and more inexcuſeable, than either Jew or Heathen, for they had no ſuch Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly example, nor no ſuch divine Precepts and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments in their Religion, but rather the contrary.</p>
            <p>Therefore a Chriſtian Perſecutor (if ſuch a thing could be) would be as a Monſter in Nature; that which is in its ſelf moſt mild, loving, gentle, harmleſs and innocent, would become the moſt wild, cruel, ravenous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring, if this could be, not only Nature, but Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101817:6"/>it ſelf would be turned quite out of courſe. Lillies would tear the Thorns, and Lambs devour the Wolves, and the Sheep prey upon the Tygers, Bears and Lyons, and the innocent Dove would devour the Birds of prey.</p>
            <p>But theſe things cannot be; therefore it may cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be concluded, and infallibly believed, that whoever is found promoting or acting Cruelty or Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, againſt any under the name and profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religon, are Wolves in Sheeps cloathing, painted Sepulchres, and profeſſing Hypocrites; neither truly loving God nor their Neighbour, which Love is the Foundation of true Religion, and by their works and doings (not by their words) they may be, and are known.</p>
            <p>Now when theſe poor deceived diſtemper'd people are known, evidently by the Signs of their diſeaſe aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, what courſe is to be taken with them, what means and medicine doth Humanity and Chriſtianity call for? And how far is the Chriſtian Magiſtrate and Law-mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, concerned about ſuch things?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, they are greatly to be pitied, becauſe the Cauſe of their diſtempers generally is <hi>Hereditary,</hi> they are born of <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> or <hi>Mahometans, Infidels</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and are trained up, and educated in their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>ways</hi> and <hi>worſhips, beliefs</hi> and <hi>opinions</hi> about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by their Parents and Tutors; ſo that they are Tinctured, if not poſſeſſed with Hereditary traditional Religion, or the Opinions of their Fore-fathers, before they know they are men, and become ſo bound with the Chains of <hi>Tradition, Cuſtom</hi> and <hi>Opinion,</hi> in the things relating to Religion, that they give up their <hi>Wills, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Conſcience,</hi> and all for the forced Maintenance and Propagation thereof, tho it be to their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101817:7"/>own hurt, and the ruin of others, not knowing nor right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtanding what they do, being captivated as above, and the cauſe in the beginning chiefly from others.</p>
            <p>Therefore even as Humanity teacheth to pity and take care of poor blind people, and ſuch who are under a great Lunary, or Diſtraction naturally as to provide for, and prevent their hurting themſelves and others; ſo it leadeth to do the ſame for thoſe that are blinded and diſtracted, through Tradition, Cuſtom, Superſtitious Education, and opinion: and Chriſtianity teacheth a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Leſſon, even to pray for them; and with all mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, gentleneſs, tenderneſs and love, to endeavour their better information, in order to their deliverance and redemption from under thoſe ſinful cuſtoms and falſe opinions, whoſe Tyranny and oppreſſion makes not only Fools, but wiſe men mad.</p>
            <p>And for ſo doing, Chriſt himſelf hath left Example, not only in his divine Precepts and Commandments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, but in his own perſon, when he prayed for thoſe great profeſſing people the Jews, whom he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wept over, and expreſſed as much tenderneſs towards them, as a Hen hath towards her Chicken; and when they were upon the point of Executing their utmoſt of envy, rage, blindneſs and madneſs upon him, he ſaid, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do;</hi> and his Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>if they had known him, they would not have Crucified the Lord of Glory:</hi> this he knew to be true by woful experience himſelf, being blind and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, while a mad zealous Perſecutor: ignorance and envy hath been, and is the cauſe of all violence againſt the Righteous, and about Religion throughout all former Ages, and let the pretence be what it will, it hath no other foundation in this Age.</p>
            <p>All the Inventers of <hi>Creeds, Articles</hi> of <hi>Faith, Maſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>books,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101817:7"/>Common-prayer-books, Directories,</hi> and other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers of ſet forms of worſhip in whole Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom have been prone to Curſe perſecution againſt ſuch as comply not therewith: eſpecially when any one of them becomes National, and are poſſeſſed of great Revenues for the maintenance of the ſame; that is as Oyl to the Flame that hath devoured many, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed the whole Chriſtian World.</p>
            <p>Therefore it concerns the Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and Law-makers, to take care that none of thoſe people have power and opportunity to force and compel un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der corporal pains and penalties, the obſervation of their inventions and preſcriptions; for ſuch things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not from true Religion, but from the <hi>opinion and imagination</hi> about it, and as hath been ſaid, is inconſiſtent with it.</p>
            <p>Now the great men of this Iſland of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> who are and may be concerned to make and execute Laws, may in the firſt place ſee it abſolutely needful to abrogate and demoliſh all ſuch Laws about Religion, as have proceeded from people in the State above: as all Laws to baniſh, hang, burn, Stigmatize, whip and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon the Bodies of people for matters of meer Religion and Conſcience are; and to make and eſtabliſh ſuch Laws in the room thereof, as may prevent any ſort, or Sect of people to hurt, rifle and ſpoil their Neighbours and Country-men, becauſe they may diſſer in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and practice in matters of worſhip and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and that may command and enjoyn morality and good Neighbourhood, among men of different perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about forms of worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> herein the Nation would be made happy, even in your imitating the great God of <hi>Love, Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> in the midſt of all <hi>vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,</hi> and the light of his countenance would ſhine in you, and upon you.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101817:8"/>
            <p>And now you have a Seaſon for ſo doing: The King in his late tender gracious Declaration, hath <hi>out-done</hi> all the Princes of Chriſtendom, and ſet them a glorious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, by following which they may make themſelves and all their people happy: He is a Prince of great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and experience, and hath thereby made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Throne in the Hearts and affections of his people: And if you do but caſt an impartial Eye void of <hi>preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice</hi> and <hi>opinion</hi> you will find none throughout the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but ſuch who are captivated thereby, and have been, and would be again perſecutors about the mode and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Religion, and Church Ceremonies (it being the Nature of every Sect, <hi>private</hi> Spirit and opinion, to uſe force and compulſion when able) becauſe falſe opinion, blind Zeal, and traditional Faith, is ſome of the Wine, with which the Whores cup is filled, whereby thoſe that drink freely thereof, ſuppoſing it to be the Wine of the Kingdom, are made Drunk, intoxicated and mad therewith, as hath been ſaid, you will find none but ſuch that are for the continuation of ſuch Laws, as would ſpoil men of their lives, liberties, and Eſtates in this World, about the things of another, about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of meer Religion and Conſcience, about humane inventions, carnal ordinances, and circumſtances of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Worſhip, to the great ſhame and ſcandal of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, which never came into the World at that Door; neither did it ever uſe or prevail by ſuch means, nor ever will; being certainly true, that all that are found in that way and work, under the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, they are in the Degeneration from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thereof, and they are but a Sect, though they may call themſelves Univerſal or National Church; have a care of Jealouſies, and falſe Suggeſtions; and take heed of making concluſions, that the deſign of the Kings Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101817:8"/>is only to introduce the Roman Catholick Sect; herein you may abuſe the beſt of Kings, for tho he hath declared himſelf to be of that perſwaſion, as to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet it is moſt apparent, that his underſtanding is ſo far divinely illuminated, that he owns it not in the worſt parts of it, <hi>viz. force, violence</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, declaration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>We cannot but heartily wiſh, as it will eafily be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that all the people of our Dominions were Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Catholick Church, yet we humbly thank Almighty God it is, and hath of a long time been our conſtant ſence and opinion (which upon divers occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we have declared) that <hi>Conſcience ought not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, nor People forced in matters of meer Religion.</hi> It has even been contrary to our inclination, as we think it is to the intereſt of Government, which it deſtroys by ſpoiling Trade, Depopulating Countries, and diſcouraging Strangers, and finally that it never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the end,</q> for which it was imployed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is as much ſaid in ſo many words, as can well be, to <hi>ſignifie</hi> that they proceed from a profound Judgment, a true and conſtant Sence, a right opinion, great reaſon, a perfect ſight of the true intereſt of Government, and all confirm'd by obſervation and experience, with thanks to Almighty God for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now for any to ſurmiſe and imagin, that there is a Snake in this fair Graſs, and that there is ſome grand evil deſign to be uſhered in thereby, is great Ingratitude, the effect of bad Jealouſie, and the Fruit of ſome fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sect, that cannot live at eaſe while their Neighbours are free from trouble.</p>
            <p>Indeed if the King acted without any of thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent qualifications before mentioned, barely <hi>as a Roman Catholick,</hi> moving only by the Dictates of that Church,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101817:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>you and the Nation might have ground to fear, that there is an <hi>Adder</hi> in the Graſs, which is much more dangerous than a Snake, and that it is with deſign not only to gain equal liberty for the Roman Catholicks, but alſo to make them capable in time to ſuppreſs all others, as the Nature of that Sect is with cruelty and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, as this and many Nations can witneſs; but to think that this is the deſign of the King, is the worſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation that malice and envy can put upon the words and doings of ſo great and juſt a Prince, whom none can juſtly charge with playing the Hypocrite, and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling with God and Man, as ſuch thoughts would inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate, and he hath been a Sufferer for Conſcience ſake himſelf, while a Subject (tho of the greateſt Rank) and when in the greateſt power, who can ſay that ever he moved or put forward the making or executing thoſe Penal Laws about Religion, by which many mens lives, Liberties and Eſtates, have been deſtroyed in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Let all ſuch thoughts and jealouſies be laid aſide, and with the King give humble thanks to Almighty God, that he hath placed ſuch a one upon the Throne, whoſe Heart he hath enclined to imitate his divine Majeſty in being kind, merciful and juſt to all, without reſpect to <hi>Perſons,</hi> or <hi>Opinions,</hi> and be ready to concur with him in his juſt deſign, and Chriſtian intentions of aboliſhing all Penal Laws, about that which is accounted Religion, but indeed is more properly <hi>Opinion,</hi> for the Chriſtian Religion, and Penal Laws to enforce it, were always inconſiſtent, as hath been hinted; 'tis <hi>Opinion</hi> and not pure <hi>Religion</hi> that hath deviſed, and ſet up Penal Laws to defend and propagate it.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Religion came into the World without the approbation, conſent, or aſſiſtance of the great Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101817:9"/>Doctors and Rabbies, and other great men of the World, they were all diſturbed at the appearance of Chriſt the Author of it, and conſulted how to deſtroy him, and the higheſt profeſſors of God and Religion in that Age, ſtudied and ſought all ways and means how to ſuppreſs and prevent the ſetting up and ſpreading the Chriſtian Religion, but it being founded in the Truth in the inward parts, which God loves it grew and prevailed in the Hearts of people, amidſt all oppoſition working powerfully in the Minds, Hearts, and underſtandings of Jews, Greeks, Barbarians, Schithyans, bond and free, making a real chaing in the inward man, not in the opinion or notion of things only, but they were renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Spirit of their minds, their Hearts were purified, conſciences rectified, their underſtandings illuminated, and their Converſations was ſuch as became the Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>Brotherly love, Kindneſs, patience, long Suffering with Innocency,</hi> and other Fruits of the Spirit abounded among them; this was their State when Laws and Edicts of Men were againſt them, who had neither Sword, nor Penal Laws on their ſide; they were far degenerated from the Nature, tho not from the Name Chriſtian, when they called to the civil Magiſtrate for Penal Laws, they were then run into Sects, Sides and Opinions, and into diſputes and quarrellings with one another about them, envying, hating and perſecuting one another, becoming as they got power as cruel to each other, as the Heathen had been to them, forcing and impoſing their Faiths, Forms and Opinions, by baniſhments, Torments and Death, to the great ſhame of the Chriſtian Religion; the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of which is love, peace and good will to all men, and the means it prevailes by, and the Weapons it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers with, are not carnal but ſpiritual, <hi>Domonſtration, Perſwaſion</hi> and <hi>Conviction,</hi> whoſoever hath, or <hi>deſire</hi> to uſe any other Weapons about the Chriſtian Religion, are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101817:10"/>certainly deceived and miſtaken ſo far as to take falſe opinion for true Religion.</p>
            <p>Now the chief end of Mageſtracy, Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among men, is to preſerve and defend their proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, liberties and lives, from ſuch as would ſpoil and rob them of either, and among all the Beaſts of prey, blind Zeal, miſguided Conſcience, private dark ſelfiſh opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are moſt ravenous, this Wolf in Sheeps cloathing hath ſharp Teeth and cruel Claws, and a wild untamed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Spirit. Notwithſtanding his pretence of Zeal and Conſcience for the Chriſtian Religion, 'tis the Spirit of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> that murtherer and Perſecutor about Sacrifice and Worſhip.</p>
            <p>But whoſoever is led by his religious, or rather irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious opinions, to endeavour the hurt or ruin of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Neighbour, about matters of meer Religion and Conſcience, if he accompliſh and effect the ſame, he is an <hi>evil doer</hi> and ought to ſuffer as an <hi>evil doer:</hi> And he that hath good will to all, and ſeeks the good of all, and hurts no man (tho he be of a contrary mind and judgment to him, and erroneous <hi>opinions</hi>) he is a <hi>well doer;</hi> and the Laws of God and all good men, who are appointed to judge and rule for God, are a Terror to the one, and a praiſe, defence and encouragement to the other.</p>
            <p>Now as you are Engliſh men, your very Native Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity (where it is not ſpoiled with falſe opinion) leads you to be ſociable, kind and neighbourly, but where the principle and the precepts of the Chriſtian Religion prevailes upon you, and poſſeſs your Judgments, <hi>As to do to others, as you would have them do to you, do good to all, overcome evil with good, love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, where theſe univerſal precepts of Chriſtianity prevailes in you, (from the principle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101817:10"/>it makes you excel your Native Humanity, and will incline your Hearts to concur with things that are ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereto, and to abrogate the contrary.</p>
            <p>Did you and the Princes, and great Monarhs of the World but know, and experience, what eaſe, what peace, what pleaſure, what profit, what true honour, glory and greatneſs, doth and would attend the true obſervation of theſe Chriſtian precepts, beyond all that can be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe invented, or deviſed, you and they would be in love therewith, and ſeek only the advancement thereof, becauſe tending to the univerſal good of mankind, not only in this Nation, but throughout all Nations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth. It is but a little while ago, ſince moſt of the Courts and Magiſtrates of <hi>England,</hi> were troubled with people about Non-conformity, their Houſes brok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en up, their goods ſeized and taken away; not leaving ſome a Bed to lye on, nor a Pot to dreſs their Food in, nor a Stool to ſit on, nor Tools to work with; ſome places, their Trades deſtroyed, and their Bodies impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned: And if any Magiſtrate did but incline to kindneſs and moderation, people of the baſer ſort called Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, who lived upon the Prey, would threaten them with 100 <hi>l.</hi> damage, ſo that many that were not willing to make havock of people, and their Goods, were forced to pleaſe thoſe Beaſts of prey, which was a trouble and exerciſe to many, even of thoſe called the Church of <hi>England</hi>-men themſelves, whoſe Humanity was not quite deſtroyed with their Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>All which the King in his gracious Declaration hath eaſed you and the people of, for which he is worthy of all gratitude and thankfulneſs, from his Subjects of all degrees, but eſpecially from his Non-conforming Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who were a people deſigned for ruin, ſo that they are ingaged to pray, that he may receive from Almighty
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101817:11"/>God a hundred fold miniſtred into his own Boſom.</p>
            <p>So if you join with the King in laying aſide all Penal Laws in matters Eccleſiaſtical, and ſet people free from danger of loſing their liberty and property for Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity; and with him as your wiſdom may deviſe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the like to be made again in future Ages; you will not only pleaſe the King and the Nation, and all people therein, except thoſe in whom <hi>corrupt Intereſt, falſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and fearful Jealouſies</hi> prevailes, but you will alſo go ſar in anſwering and fulfilling thoſe Chriſtian divine Precepts, which are according to the juſt and righteous principle of God in all men, and where it is not Stifled, Crucified and Buried, it will ariſe and Anſwer to your juſt and righteous doings, and you will have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thereof in your ſelves, and will become examplary to the Nations round about, who when they ſhall hear, ſee and behold the bleſſed Fruits and effects, which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly will follow your ſo doing, may be ſtirred up to imitate and follow ſo glorious Example.</p>
            <p>If you conſult with any that are fill'd with <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> eſpecially ſuch who have a corrupt Intereſt to ſecure, (which cannot ſtand in that pomp and power they would have it, without force and violence,) you will be diſcouraged in ſo good a Work, as the preventing people from hurting one another about the opinion of Religion is.</p>
            <p>Have a care of men of that temper, your buſineſs is to ſhew forth a noble and generous Spirit, Eying the good of all without reſpect to perſons, or opinions, and to concur with the King in providing ſo, that it ſhall not be in the power of the preſent and after Ages, to ſpoil and perſecute one another about matters of meer Religion and Conſcience.</p>
            <p>It is an ancient Maxim, <hi>That the Truth is great and will prevail,</hi> and the Chriſtian Religion and Worſhip that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101817:11"/>ſtands therein, requires neither Penal Laws, nor Arms to ſet it up nor defend it, if any ſhall call upon you or counſel you to continue and uphold ſuch Laws, ſearch them to the bottom, and you will find they have ſome private Belly Intereſt to carry on, and that there lies a venemous biting Adder in their Graſs, and that their Religion is ſuch, as cannot ſtand in the pomp of it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Penal Laws.</p>
            <p>'Tis the Whore, (the falſe Church) that rides up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Scarlet colour'd Beaſt, ſhe can't ſtand alone, nor walk upon her own Legs; and it is ſhe that hath cryed to Kings, Emperors, Parliaments and great men, to force and compel people to bear her dead weight, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pains of Baniſhment, Hanging, Burning and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, and the loſs of all the good things of this World without conformity to her, wherever you find this cry, aſſure your ſelves that it is not from the <hi>Spouſe of Chriſt,</hi> it is not the true Mother that would have the living Child divided or cut in pieces, becauſe her own is ſmothered and dead.</p>
            <p>You may infallibly conclude, that it is not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical and primitive Spirit of Chriſtianity, that would have mens <hi>Liberties, Lives</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> ſpoiled, and rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated about matters of worſhip and conſcience, tho their worſhip was wrong and erronious, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience deſiled and miſin-formed, and therein making conſcience of things which they ought not, nor may not, when with tenderneſs and meekneſs, they are better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd and inſtructed.</p>
            <p>The true Churches power, as hath been ſaid, was and is <hi>Demonſtration, Perſwaſion</hi> and <hi>Conviction,</hi> and her <hi>Weapons Spiritual</hi> and not <hi>Carnal,</hi> if any dare ſay and affirm, that the New Teſtament way and means to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert or proſelite the World to Chriſtianity, was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, or that the Chriſtian principle, <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101817:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Chriſt,</hi> can admit of any other means in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtian Religion; let them come forth and ſhew the proof in the New Teſtament, or elſe let them not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> regarded.</p>
            <p>In this the Children of God are manifeſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Children of the Devil, whoſoever doth not Righteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are not of God, neither he that loveth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Brother, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If a Man ſay I love God, and hateth his Brother, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Lyar, for he that loveth not his Brother whom he hath ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen,</hi> 1 John 4.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
